<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of His Highnes, by the advice of his Council setting forth, on the behalf of this Commonwealth, the justice of their cause against Spain. Friday the 26. of October, 1655. Ordered by His Highness the Lord Protector, and the Council, that this declaration be forthwith printed and published. Hen: Scobel, Clerk of the Council.</title>
            <title>Orders in Council. 1655-10-26</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Lord Protector (1653-1658 : O. Cromwell)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80912</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899607</idno>
  <idno type="VID">154135</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248524957</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7081A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213565</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899607</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99899607e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80912)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154135)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2401:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of His Highnes, by the advice of his Council setting forth, on the behalf of this Commonwealth, the justice of their cause against Spain. Friday the 26. of October, 1655. Ordered by His Highness the Lord Protector, and the Council, that this declaration be forthwith printed and published. Hen: Scobel, Clerk of the Council.</title>
                  <title>Orders in Council. 1655-10-26</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Lord Protector (1653-1658 : O. Cromwell)</author>
                  <author>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Council of State. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>re-printed by Christopher Higgins, in Harts-Close, over against the Trone-Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLV. [1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Spain --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  Foreign relations --  Spain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154135:1"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF HIS HIGHNES, By the Advice of HIS COUNCIL; Setting forth, On the behalf of this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> the Justice of their Cause Against SPAIN.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Friday the 26. of <hi>October,</hi> 1655.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>ORdered by His Highness the Lord Protector, and the Council, That this Declaration be forthwith Printed and Published.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Hen: Scobel, Clerk of the Council.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>EDINBURGH, Re-printed by <hi>Christopher Higgins,</hi> in <hi>Harts</hi>-Close, over against the Trone-Church. MDCLV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:154135:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:154135:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>Declaration</hi> of His Highness, by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of His Council; Setting forth, on the behalf of this COMMON-VVEALTH, the Justice of their Cause Against SPAIN.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Just and most Reasonable Causes and Grounds of Our late Enterprize upon some Islands, possessed by the Subjects of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> in the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> are very obvious to any that shall reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the posture wherein the said King and his People have alwaies stood, in relation to the English Nation in those parts of <hi>America,</hi> which hath been no other then a continual state of open War and Hostility; at the first most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly begun by them, and ever since in like sort continued and prosecuted, contrary to the Common Right and Law of Nations, and the particular Treaties between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true indeed, That of late Years the English have for the most part been Patients, and upon the Defensive onely, which may possibly occasion some to look upon the late Expedition into the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> as an Entrance into a new War, and not, as it was indeed, the prosecution of a War already in being, and still (notwithstanding all Endeavours on the part of this State, for setling a firm Peace and friendly Commerce in those parts) obstinatly continued and carried on by the Spaniards; who, as oft as they have opportunity, without any just Cause or Provocation at all, cease not to kill and slaughter, nay, sometimes in cold Blood, to murder the People of this Nation, spoiling their Goods and Estates, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying their Colonies and Plantations, taking also their Ships (if they meet with any) upon those Seas, and using them in all things as Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, or rather as Rovers and Pyrates, for so they most injuriously and ignominiously brand all Nations (except themselves) which shall presume to sail upon those Seas, upon no other or better Right or Title, then that of the Popes Donation, and their first Discovering some parts of the <hi>West Indies;</hi> whereupon they would appropriate to themselves the sole Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niory of that <hi>New World;</hi> of which most absurd Pretension, there will be occasion to speak more largely, when We come to consider the Causes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154135:3"/> why the Spaniards should think it reasonable for them to exercise all manner of Hostility in those parts against the English, in so far as to make such of them, as by stress of weather, Shipwrack, or other like Casualty, are cast upon those Coasts, Prisoners, nay, Slaves; and yet to accompt it a great Injury, and Breach of the Peace (even here in <hi>Europe</hi>) for the English to attempt any thing upon them in those parts by way of Reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, and for their just Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>But although the King of <hi>Spain's</hi> Embassadors (emboldened upon the assurance of a prevalent Spanish Faction, alwaies in the Council of the late King and his Father) have had the Confidence to make most ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and irrational Complaints and Demands, upon any thing done in that kinde by the English; yet would not the said Kings (though too much addicted to the Spaniards) ever tie their own Subjects hands, where the Spaniards held their hands to be loose, but suffered them to repel Force by Force, and to exercise Acts of Hostility in those parts against the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who never would keep any Peace there; insomuch that about the Year One thousand six hundred and fourty, when this Question was brought into debate before the Council of the late King, the Spanish Ambassador demanding the stop of certain Vessels then in the River, ready to set sail for <hi>America,</hi> with Commissions to exercise Acts of Hostility there against the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> And the English, upon a Demand made of Commerce in the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> by the Lords of the Council appointed for that Affair, being denied the same, they determined that the Ships should proceed in their Enterprizes, which they did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
            <p>Thus far the late Kings owned their Subjects in the War they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in those parts, upon their private accompt, although through the prevalency of the fore-mentioned Spanish Faction, they would never af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford them that publick Protection which was due unto them, and which was suitable to the Honour and Interest of this Nation. And it would have been as Dishonourable and Unworthy for Us, who, through the goodness and providence of God, were so well furnisht with Ships of War fit for Foreign Service, to have let them lie rotting at home, rather than to have employed them for the just Revenge of so much <hi>English</hi> (why may we not also say) <hi>Indian blood,</hi> so unjustly, so inhumanly, and so cruelly spilt by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in those parts, <hi>Since God hath made of one Blood, all Nations of Men, for to dwell on all the face of the Earth, and hath determined the times before appointed, and the bounds of their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation;</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:154135:3"/> And certainly, at one time or another, by some hand or other, God will have an accompt of the Innocent Blood of so many Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of <hi>Indians,</hi> so barbarously Butchered by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and of the Wrong and Jnjustice that hath been done unto them.</p>
            <p>But We shall have no need to have recourse unto the common Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood between all Mankinde, which in some sort may interest them in the horrid, and enormious Injuries of each other, the blood and spoils of our own Countreymen, being sufficient to warrant the late Expedition, besides the Consideration of Present Interest, and Future Security to this Nation, and all its Allyes, especially of the Protestant Religion, with sundry other Reasons and Motives, which were Inducements to that Undertaking, the which it is not Our Businesse (at present) particularly to declare, but the Justice and Warrantablenesse thereof; For the better cleering whereof, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifesting what hath been already alleadged in generall, it will be neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to cast our eyes a little back, and to take a view of the Transacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and the state they have been in, with Relation to each other, since the Reformation of Religion, and the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the <hi>West-Indies;</hi> which two great Revolutions, happening neer about the same time, did very much alter the State of Affairs in the World, especially in Relation to the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Spanish</hi> Nations, who ever since have taken a Different, and almost a contrary Measure of their Interest, from what they did before. For, although the late King, and His Father, contrary to the Stream and Current of the Affections and Hearts of this Nation, patched up two Treaties of Peace with <hi>Spain;</hi> yet those New Principles, begotten through the Difference of Religion, and the Continuall Quarrels in the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> together with the <hi>Spaniards</hi> perpetual Jealousies of the <hi>English,</hi> in respect of his Treasure there, as they have rendred the late Endeavours of this Commonwealth Fruitless, as to the settling of a Firm Peace, upon Just and Honourable Terms, so were they the true Causes that induced <hi>Philip</hi> the Second King of <hi>Spain,</hi> in the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to break that Ancient and long un-interrupted League, which this Nation had with his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessours, both of the <hi>Burgundian</hi> and <hi>Castillian</hi> Line, and entering in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a War with the said Queen, to Design (and depending a Treaty of Peace) in the year One thousand five hundred eighty eight, to attempt a totall Conquest of this Nation, which must needs ly close by <hi>English</hi> mens hearts, and will not easily out of their Mindes. And albeit there was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154135:4"/> after, a kind of Peace and Commerce in <hi>Europe</hi> (though never such a one, as that an English man durst own his Religion in the Spanish Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, or keep a Bible in his House or Ship) yet in the <hi>West-Indies</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> would never since admit either of Peace or Commerce, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding that both are expresly accorded by the Treaty made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, King of <hi>England,</hi> and the Emperor, <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, in the year One thousand five hundred fourty two, wherein Peace and free Commerce is agreed upon between the two States, and the Subjects of each Prince in all the Dominions, Ports, and Territories of each other whatsoever, without any exception of the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> though at that time in possession of the said Emperor.</p>
            <p>And as to the Article of Peace in all parts of the World; It is express<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contained in all the Treaties of Peace, that ever were between the two Nations; neither is there any restriction of Commerce in any Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty before that of One thousand six hundred and four, whereunto the last Treaty, in the year One thousand six hundred and thirty, doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly agree, as to this matter. In which two last Treaties, Commerce is agreed in all and singular the Dominions of both States; <hi>In which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the War between</hi> Philip <hi>the Second King of</hi> Spain, <hi>and</hi> Elizabeth <hi>Queen of</hi> England, <hi>there had been Commerce between the two Kingdoms, like and according to the use and observance of the Ancient Leagues and Treaties made before the said time:</hi> These are the words of the Treaties, which leave the matter doubtfull, and so King <hi>James</hi> was contented to slubber up a Peace with <hi>Spain,</hi> when he resumed the Treaty, which was on foot a little before the death of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> and wherein, amongst other things, she gave her Commissioners Instructions to insist upon Commerce, and a Free Trade in the <hi>West-Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But King <hi>James</hi> (who was exceeding fond of a Peace with <hi>Spain</hi>) was content to leave that Point in such sort, as that either part might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret the Article in their own sense; although if those words of <hi>The use and observance of the Ancient Leagues and Treaties</hi> are to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood (as in Reason they ought) according to what of Right ought to have been observed, and not according to what in Fact was practised on the Spaniards part, in direct violation thereof, (which was continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all matter of complaint on the part of the English, and of quarrel between the two Nation) it is very evident by the express words of the Ancient Treaties, That the English were to have Commerce, as well as Peace, in all the Spanish Dominions whatsoever.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:154135:4"/>
            <p>But if the measure of the Observance of the Ancient Leagues and Treaties, is to be taken from the manifest Violation and Infringement of them, the Spaniards may have some colour to interpret that Clause of the last Treaties, as restraining Commerce in those parts. And yet, for the first half of the time between the afore-mentioned Treaty 1542. and the breaking forth of the War between Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> the Second King of <hi>Spain,</hi> there appeareth as much in matter of Fact for the Permission, as for the Prohibition of Trade in those parts. And after, when the Spaniards utterly refused Commerce, the Exchange of Wares was turned into the Enchange of Blows, and of Powder and Shot, as well before the War between Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond King of <hi>Spain,</hi> as after the Peaces made by King <hi>James</hi> in the year 1604, and by his Son in the year 1630, yet so, as that it did not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the Commerce in these parts of <hi>Europe;</hi> although now the King of <hi>Spain</hi> by his late Embargo, hath first interpreted the Quarrels of those parts, to extend unto these of <hi>Europe</hi> also.</p>
            <p>But We do not insist either upon the interpretation of the Treaties, or Right of Commerce thereby, or otherwise, as that whereon We have any need to state our Quarrel, it being founded upon Clear and Undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputable Grounds, as We shall presently declare; yet such things as may not be so necessary Causes whereupon to found and begin a War, may be reasonable Impediments to the concluding of a Peace, or at least to the renewing of a League, wherein We cannot have so much allowed, as in former Leagues have been admitted, and in reason may be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; which may serve also for an Answer to that Question, Why, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving renewed our Leagues with all other Nations, We have not done it with the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and that We have not demanded as a Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof; his right Eye, much lesse (as hath been said) both his Eyes, because We would not be at the Mercy of a cruell Inquisition, where We are admitted to Commerce, and would be admitted to Commerce, where We ought not to be excluded from it, neither by the Ancient Treaties, nor of Common Right; for although the King of <hi>Spain</hi> hath formerly taken upon him to prescribe us Bounds of Trade, upon a Law made by the Pope, inhibiting all Trade &amp; Commerce with Turks, Jews &amp; other Infidels,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Will. Stephens</hi> of <hi>Bristol,</hi> with divers Merchants of <hi>London,</hi> in the year <hi>1606.</hi> and <hi>1607,</hi> having three of their Ships on the Coast of <hi>Barbary,</hi> in trade with the People of that Countrey, the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Men of War ranging that Coast, and finding these Ships at anchor in <hi>Saphio</hi> and <hi>Sancta Cruce</hi> Road, rifled them of what they had, saying, <hi>That the King their Master would not give liberty of Trade with Infidels;</hi> Their losses amounted to above two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pounds.</note> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154135:5"/> upon that Accompt, his Ships of War in time of Peace, have taken and spoiled Our Ships in other parts of the world, as well as in the <hi>West-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;</hi> And although by the like Authority from the Pope, and upon the Title of his Donation, he claimeth a Right over the Indians, as if they were all his Subjects, even those that actually are not under his Power or Obedience; yet We acknowledge no such Right, neither in the Pope nor King of <hi>Spain,</hi> to take away from the Indians the Right of their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or from Us the Right which We have by the Law of Nature, and of Nations, of Converse and Commerce with them, especially such of them as are not actually under the Power and subjection of the King of <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Impediment to the renewing of the League with <hi>Spain,</hi> is manifest and notorious, and such as cutteth off all Assurance from Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Ministers and Agents employed into the Dominions of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> upon any Negotiations of Amity, or other Transactions between the two States, where the Prince holdeth forth such Principles, as render him uncapable to give Security and Protection to Ambassadors and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Ministers, against Assassinations and outragious Attempts of violence upon their Persons, which, for the preserving of Entercourse, and a good Understanding between Princes and States, by the Law of Nations, have alwaies been held most inviolable, and more sacred than those Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, whose Priviledges (derived from the Authority of the Pope and Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) have been pretended to elude and avoid the Execution of Justice from time to time demanded, and insisted upon by this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, upon the Assassinates of Mr. <hi>Anthony Ascham,</hi> sent under a Publick Character from this Commonwealth into <hi>Spain,</hi> to procure and settle a good Understanding between the two Nations; for which barbarous Murder, no satisfaction or condign punishment upon the said Assassinates, could ever be obtained, though required<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by a Clause in a Letter sent from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and signed by their Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, to the King of</hi> Spain <hi>in</hi> January 1650. <hi>viz.</hi> We require of your Majesty, and insist upon it, That Satisfaction be at length given to Publick Justice, touching the flagitious Murder of <hi>Anthony Ascham,</hi> Our Resident; And the rather, because after due Punishment inflicted upon the Authors of a Wickedness of such a nature, We shall not doubt to send Our Embassador to your Royal Court, to treat of those things which may be of Advantage, aswel to your Majesty, as to this Our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth. On the contrary, if We should suffer that Blood, notorious by so many circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, to passe unavenged, We shall necessarily in the sight of God, Our only Deliverer, and the everlasting Fountain of Our Mercies, and before the whole English Nation, become Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in the Guilt; especially if We shall afterwards send another English-man into that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, where it is lawful for any, without fear of punishment, to murder him; But We for Our parts have so high an esteem of your Majesty, That we cannot easily beleeve your Royal Power within your own Dominions, to be subjected to any foreign Power whatsoever.</note> by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154135:5"/> and often insisted upon by the Council of State in their behalf, which hath been a continuall and most just Obstacle, to the renewing of the Leagues between the two Nations, and might well be esteemed (according to what hath been practised amongst other Nations, upon the like occasion) a just Cause of a War.</p>
            <p>But as to the state of Our Quarrell in the <hi>West-Indies;</hi> Whereas We have Colonies in <hi>America,</hi> as well in Islands as upon the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, upon as good and a better Title then the Spaniards have any, and have as good a right to Sail in those Seas as themselves; yet without any just Cause or Provocation (and where the Question of Commerce was not at all in the Case) they have notwithstanding, continually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded, in an Hostile maner, Our Colonies, slain Our Countrymen, taken Our Ships and Goods, destroyed Our Plantations, made Our People Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners and Slaves, and have continued so doing from time to time, till the very time that We undertook the late Expedition against them.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, contrary to what hath been formerly practised, they have also made an Embargo of Our Ships, and Arrested the Persons and Goods of all English men in <hi>Spain;</hi> so that whether We look to the parts of <hi>America</hi> or of <hi>Europe,</hi> they are the first beginners and causers of the War, and of all the Blood and Inconvenience that may ensue thereupon.</p>
            <p>The instances of the continuall Acts of Hostility, and Cruelties, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the Spaniards against the English in the <hi>West-Indies</hi> in the times of Peace, both from the Year, 1604, when a Peace was made by King <hi>James,</hi> till the War broke out again, and from the conclusion of the last Peace in the Year 1630, till this time, are very many, and very Barbarous, and Bloody, We shall content Our selves with some<note n="*" place="margin">Ship cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Ulisses,</hi> being in Trade upon the Coast of <hi>Guiana,</hi> when the Merchants and Marriners went on shore upon the Faith and Oaths of <hi>Don Berreo</hi> Governour of that place; to which Oaths the Marriners giving Credit, were notwithstanding Thirty of them suddenly t k en and committed, and Letters written from the Governour to the Merchant, That it was true he had taken Thirty of his men prisoners, for that divers Strangers that had formerly traded there, had deceived him of twenty thousand Duckets, but if that he would send him the Twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Duckets, then he vowed presently to send him all his Thirty men aboard safe, and then to continue their Trade also: whereupon, the Merchants sent him in Plate and Goods, his desired Sum; which when the Governour <hi>Don Berreo</hi> had received, he caused all the Thirty men to be strangled to trees, except the Chirurgeon of the Ship, which was kept alive to cure the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours disease. This Ransom with other Losses there, amounted to Seven thousand pounds.</note> few.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:154135:6"/>
            <p>After the Peace concluded in the Year 1605, a Ship called the <hi>Mary, Ambrose Birch</hi> being Master, was in Trade upon the North-side of <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaniola</hi> in the <hi>West-Indies;</hi> and the Master with six of his Company being enticed on Shore by a Priest called Father <hi>John,</hi> to see some Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, under promise of secure and fair Trading, and twelve <hi>Spaniards</hi> going aboard the Ship to view the <hi>English</hi> Wares; whilst the <hi>English</hi> Merchants were shewing them their Merchandize, nothing doubting of any fraud, the Watch-word being given from the shore by the Priest, every <hi>Spaniard</hi> drew out a great Knife, and stabbed all the <hi>English</hi> men aboard, except two that leaped into the Sea, and the rest on the shore were put to strange deaths, and the Master himself was stripped naked, and bound to a tree with cords, and so pinched and stung to death, being naked, by Mosqueto's; where continuing about twenty hours, a Negro hearing a man roar, and cry in that extremity, and finding him, ran him through with his Lance: This Ship and Goods was worth five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand four hundred pounds.</p>
            <p>Another Ship called the <hi>Archer</hi> was the same Year taken near to <hi>Sancto Domingo,</hi> and all her men executed: This Ship was worth Thirteen hundred pounds.</p>
            <p>Another Ship called the <hi>Amity of London</hi> with her Pinace, was taken by <hi>Don Lewis Faczardo</hi> Governour of the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Armado, the Ship and Goods were Confiscated, and the Merchants and Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners all cast into the Sea, except one Boy to do them service: This Ship and Pinace were worth Five thousand six hundred pounds.</p>
            <p>Another Ship called the <hi>Scorn,</hi> having her men on shore, upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of the Spaniards Oaths, they were notwithstanding all strangled to trees: where their Owners lost their Ship and Goods, amounting to Fifteen hundred pounds.</p>
            <p>In the Year one thousand six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and six,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>John Davies</hi> lost two Pina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with all the Goods in them, and had all the men in the same murthered; to the overthrow of the Voyage, by which he lost Three thousand five hundred pounds.</note> a Ship called the <hi>Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> was taken near the <hi>Tortugas</hi> by the Spanish men of War, being worth Four thousand and three hundred pounds.</p>
            <p>In the same Year, another Ship called the <hi>Lark,</hi> was taken by <hi>Don Lewis Faczardo,</hi> and confiscated with her whole Lading, being worth Four thousand five hundred and seventy pounds.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:154135:6"/>
            <p>Aonther Ship called the <hi>Castor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi>
               <note place="margin">One other Ship belonging to divers Merchants of <hi>London,</hi> (whereof the Master was <hi>John Lock</hi>) was by the Spanish Forces taken near the Island of <hi>Tortugas,</hi> for trading and cutting Wood; and for the same the Ship and Goods confiscated, and most of the Men taken and executed, and the rest committed to the Gallyes to the loss of Five thousand three hundred pounds.</note> was taken by the Spaniards upon the Coast of <hi>Florida,</hi> which they confiscated, and executed all the Men in her, or kept them Slaves, for they could never be heard of since: This Ship with her Merchandize was worth Fifteen thousand pounds.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1608, a Ship called <hi>The Richard</hi> of <hi>Plimouth,</hi> whereof was Captain one <hi>Henry Challins,</hi> being set forth by the Lord Chief Justice <hi>Popham,</hi> Sir <hi>Ferdinando Gorges,</hi> and others for <hi>Virginia,</hi> and by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Storms being driven to the southward of the <hi>Canary</hi> Islands, and then bending her course for the place they intended, in 27 degrees, by chance they met with Eleven sayl of Spanish Ships coming from <hi>St. Domingo,</hi> which took the said Ship, notwithstanding that the Captain shewed the Kings Broad Seal for his Warrant, yet the ship and Goods were confiscated, and the men most cruelly used, and sent to rowe in the Gallies; whereby was lost above Two thousand five hundred pounds.</p>
            <p>The like was done to another Ship called the <hi>Ayde,</hi> taken by <hi>Don Lewis Faczardo,</hi> under colour of friendship, and the Ship and Goods confiscated, and all the men sent to the Gallies, where some were bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to death with Cudgels, for that they refused to rowe; which Ship and Goods were worth by the Spaniards own computation, Seven thousand pounds.</p>
            <p>In the same Year, another Ship called the <hi>Anne Gallant,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Curry</hi> Master, being in Trade upon <hi>Hispaniola,</hi> the Ship and Goods were confiscated, and the whole company hanged up with papers written upon them, <hi>WHY CAME YOƲ HITHER?</hi> This Ship and Goods was worth Eight thousand pounds.</p>
            <p>These particulars may suffice to shew what Peace the Spaniards kept with Us in the <hi>West-Indies</hi> in the time of King <hi>James,</hi> who was very careful, or rather fearful, to break the Peace with them; And the like Hostile and Bloody Foot-steps, We may trace down from the time of the last Peace concluded in the year 1630, unto this very time.</p>
            <p>We shall begin with the Colonies of this Nation, setled by certain Noblemen and Gentlemen, in the Islands of <hi>Cattelina</hi> (called by them <hi>Providence</hi>) and <hi>Tortugas</hi> (by them named <hi>Association</hi>) which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154135:7"/> about the year 1629, being void of all Inhabitants, and tame Beasts or Cattel, were actually possessed by the English in time of Open War betwen <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> And the next year a Peace being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded between the two Nations, and no Claim or Reservation therein of the said Islands by the Spaniards, the late King did by his Letters Pattens under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> (notwithstanding that Peace) assume the said Island of <hi>Providence,</hi> with other adjacent Islands, as part of his own Dominions, and did grant the same to divers Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Gentlemen, and their Successors; and the next year extended his Grant to the aforementioned Island of <hi>Tortugas,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And notwithstanding that the said Adventurers were in possession of the Islands aforesaid, by the late Kings Grant, founded upon a double Right, that of Nature, the Places not being in the possession of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards or any others; and that of War, being taken in the time of War, and not excepted in the Treaty of Peace, and consequently the Spaniards pretensions thereunto (if they had any) extinguished, by their own Agreement in the <hi>Second Article</hi> of the last Treaty; And notwithstanding that neither the said Company, nor any employed by them, did give the least just Cause of Offence unto the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> or any of his Subjects, until such time as they had first assaulted their Ships and Colonies, and slain divers of the English therein, burning and destroying their Plantations; yet the Spaniards observing no Peace with the English in those parts, about the 22. of <hi>January</hi> 1632, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any just Provocation, did assault one of the Ships of the said Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, called <hi>The Sea-flower,</hi> in her peaceable Return from <hi>Providence,</hi> between the <hi>Tortugas</hi> and the Cape of <hi>Florida;</hi> in which Assault, they killed some, and wounded others in the said Ship.</p>
            <p>And after about the year 1634, the Island of <hi>Tortuga</hi> was assaulted by divers Subjects of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> in four Vessels, though there was no Provocation at all on the part of the English; in which assault, threescore or more were slain, divers wounded and taken prisoners, their Plantations spoiled, their Houses burned, their Goods to a great value carried away by the Spaniards, and the Island wholly dis-peopled thereby of the English, whereof some being hanged, and others carried prisoners to the <hi>Havana,</hi> were detained in cruel slavery, and one of them called <hi>Grymes,</hi> formerly a Gunner at <hi>Tortuga,</hi> was there barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously murthered; and some of them flying for refuge to <hi>Sancta Cruce,</hi> an Island void of Inhabitants, were pursued thither by the Spaniards in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154135:7"/> three Friggots, and there assaulted in <hi>March</hi> 1636; in which, Assault about forty of the English were slain, and the rest carried away prisoners, and used with very much hardship.</p>
            <p>And the 24 of <hi>July</hi> 1635, the Island of <hi>Providence</hi> it self was assault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Subjects of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> in two great ships and a Frig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, which maintained a Fight for divers hours, but were beaten off at that time, and forced to discontinue their Attempt, till they renewed it again about the year 1640, with twelve sail of Ships, great and small, whereof the Admirall was the <hi>Armadillo</hi> of <hi>Cartagena,</hi> one of the King of <hi>Spain's</hi> Gallioons of his Plate-Fleet; from this Fleet having landed a considerable number of Soldiers, they promised themselves the Conquest of the Island, but were again repulsed with a considerable Losse on their part; yet soon after returning with another Fleet, the Colony being then fallen into Divisions and Distractions amongst themselves, they did not think so much of making a good Defence, as of making good Conditions for themselves, which upon the Delivery up of the Island, with little or no opposition they obtained; but the Island was thereby wrested from the said Adventurers, and from the Commonwealth, to the particular Losse of the one, above Eighty thousand pounds, and to the Publique Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor and Detriment of the other; And being possessed by the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,</hi> a ship that came from <hi>New England</hi> with some People from thence, that intended to have transplanted themselves into that Island, was cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly drawn within the reach of their Canon (being ignorant that the Place was in the <hi>Spaniards</hi> hands) and got off with a great deal of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and difficulty, and the losse of the Master of the Ship (a very honest man) who was slain with a Canon shot from the Island.</p>
            <p>Neither were the <hi>Spaniards</hi> content to bound their Enterprizes against the said Adventurers within the parts of <hi>America,</hi> but also extended their acts of hostility against them to these parts of <hi>Europe;</hi> for on the 25 of <hi>December</hi> 1638. a ship called the <hi>Providence,</hi> belonging to the said Company, under the Command of Captain <hi>Thomas Newman,</hi> was assaulted and surprized two Leagues off <hi>Dongenesse</hi> upon the Coasts of <hi>England,</hi> by one Captain <hi>Springfield,</hi> Captain of a <hi>Dunkirk</hi> Man of War, and carried to <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> where the said Goods were detained (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by diverse there acknowledged to be of Thirty thousand pounds va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue) and of the <hi>English</hi> aboard the said Ship, some were slain, others wounded, and the rest after a barbarous and uncivil Usage aboard, were carried prisoners to <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> where some were used with much hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154135:8"/> till they found means to escape; And notwithstanding that the said Adventurers used all due means for to obtain satisfaction, and that the late King by his Agent, Sir <hi>Balthazar Gerbeere,</hi> and by his Letters, as well written by Secretary <hi>Cook,</hi> as with his own hand, required Justice on their behalf; yet could they not obtain Restitution of any part of the said Goods, or any Reparation in lieu thereof.</p>
            <p>There are Examples of more fresh and bleeding Memory, as that of <hi>Sancta Cruce,</hi> assaulted by the Subjects of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> from <hi>Puertorico,</hi> about the year 1651. being an Island formerly void of all Inhabitants, and possessed at that time by a Colony of the <hi>English,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Command of Captain <hi>Nicholas Philips,</hi> who, together with about a hundred more of the said Colony, were slain and butchered by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who seized the Ships in the Harbour, pillaged, burnt, and destroyed their Plantations, and Houses, and finding no more men to massacre (part of the Inhabitants escaping by flight into the Woods) the <hi>Spaniards</hi> returned to <hi>Puertorico,</hi> and gave opportunity to that mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and almost starved Remnant, to betake themselves to other adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Islands, and totally desert that of <hi>Sancta Cruce;</hi> yet the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> returned after a while from <hi>Puertorico,</hi> to hunt out and murther those who had retired themselves into the Woods, but they found means to escape their hands, and to get into other Islands.</p>
            <p>In the same year 1651. a Ship belonging to Mr. <hi>John Turner,</hi> being forced into the Port of <hi>Cumanagota</hi> by stresse of Weather, was seized by the Governour, and the Ship and Goods confiscated.</p>
            <p>The like was done to another Ship and Goods belonging to <hi>Captain Cranley.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The like had formerly been done in the same Port to a Ship belonging to Mr. <hi>John Bland,</hi> of which Captain <hi>Nicholas Philips</hi> was Commander.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And in the year 1650, a Ship be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Mr. <hi>Samuel Wilson,</hi> bound for <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and laden with Horses, was taken at Sea, and carried into the <hi>Havana,</hi> the Ship and Goods were confiscate, and most of the Men kept Prisoners, and forced to work in the Bulwarks like Slaves.</p>
            <p>The like usage had the Company belonging to a Ship of <hi>Barnstable,</hi> about two years since at <hi>Sancto Domingo</hi> in <hi>Hispaniola;</hi> which Ship, springing a Leak near <hi>Hispaniola,</hi> as she was returning from some of our Plantations in the <hi>Cariby</hi> Islands, her Company were forced to save themselves in their Boat upon <hi>Hispaniola,</hi> where they were taken Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners, and made to work like slaves in their Fortifications.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:154135:8"/>
            <p>By these Particulars (and many other of the like nature, which would be too long to rehearse) it is most apparent that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> and his Subjects, do not account themselves bound to hold any terms of Peace with the English in those parts, but continually exercise all manner of Hostility against them, and worse than Hostility; the Barbarous Usage of the English there, being so far from the Laws of Peace, that it is not agreeable to the Laws and Customs of a fair War: And yet the English must be taxed (as they are by the King of <hi>Spain</hi> in his Order for the late <hi>Embargo</hi>) as those, <hi>That had been wanting to, and Violaters of the sacred Bonds of Peace and free Commerce (so religiously</hi> (as he saies) <hi>observed by him) and that with so unthought-of and declared Hostility, as the assaulting of the City of</hi> St. Domingo <hi>in the Island of Hispaniola:</hi> which is laid down as the sole Ground and Cause of the said <hi>Embargo</hi> of the English Goods, and Arrest of their Persons in <hi>Spain,</hi> though aggravated against Us, by a Representation of <hi>His friendly Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of Our Fleets into his</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Capt. <hi>Swanley</hi> found no such kind entertain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment in the Port of <hi>Trepanny</hi> in <hi>Sicilly,</hi> where about <hi>June</hi> 1653. his Ship called the <hi>Henry Bonaventure,</hi> together with a Dutch Prize called the <hi>Peter,</hi> a great and rich Ship, were surprized in that Port within Pistol shot of their Fort, by seven Dutch men of War under the command of young <hi>Trump,</hi> through the treachery of the King of <hi>Spain's</hi> Governor of that place; whereby the Merchants concerned in the said Ship, lost to the value of sixty three thousand pounds and upwards.</note>
               <hi>Ports, where they were pleased to come, and had found it convenient for them to touch, without notice taken by his Ministers, according to the rigour of the Capitulations of Peace, between the two Crowns, which doth reciprocally prohibite the entrance into the Ports with more than six or eight Ships of War.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as himself in those words cleareth Our Fleets of any Infringement of the Capitulations in what they did, being done by leave and permis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of himself, and his Ministers, (if any such thing were done, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived at, as is alledged) and as all the world well knoweth, he was not so courteous for naught, Considering the advantage and Countenance that his Affairs of late have received from Our Fleets; so on the other side, the said King and his Ministers, have taken very little notice of the Capitulations by him mentioned, wherein it is so expresly Provided in the 23. Article thereof, that if any mis-understanding should happen to arise between the two States, <hi>The Subjects of either are thereof so to be admonished, as that they may have six months, from the time of the Monition, to transport their Merchandizes without any arrest, distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154135:9"/> or hurt in the mean season to be done, or given unto them, either in their Persons or Merchandize.</hi> In which, the said King by the late <hi>Embargo</hi> hath been manifestly wanting to the bonds of those Capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by himself remembred against Us, and his Declaration in the said Order, That acts of Hostility exercized in the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> are a breach of Peace, and of the freedom of Commerce in these parts, is of the first Impression that hitherto hath proceeded from either State; though there have not been wanting several occasions on both sides to have done it.</p>
            <p>But since the King of <hi>Spain</hi> hath both by word and deed, Declared the Treaties of Peace so to be understood, he hath consequently conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded himself to have first violated the sacred Bonds of Frendship, by so many acts of open Hostility, first exercized by him upon the English in those parts, and from time to time continued, ever since the last Treaty of Peace, as before hath been particularly declared; which is a thing so evident and notorious, that our Adversaries themselves cannot certainly have the face to deny the matter of Fact, but will choose rather to insist upon the matter of Right, and that as the King of <hi>Spain</hi> hath assumed amongst his Titles, that of <hi>Rex Indiarum;</hi> so indeed all the <hi>Indies</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> Sea, both <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> are his proper Dominions, and that they are all Enemies and Pyrats, that come there without his permission. Which truly if it were so, both We and all other Nations, ought to quit to him all We hold in those parts, and displanting our Colonies, ask him pardon for the wrong We have hitherto done unto him. But if We look into the ground of his Claim and Title, it will appear a very poor and weak Foundation, to raise so great, and so bloody a Building upon, as this hath, and is like to prove.</p>
            <p>A double Title is pretended, that of the <hi>Popes Donation,</hi> and that of first <hi>Discovery;</hi> For the former, We know very well, the <hi>Pope</hi> hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed been very free in disposing of Kingdoms and Countreys, therein being very unlike him whose <hi>Vicar</hi> he pretendeth to be, that would not take upon him so much as to be a Judge to divide Inheritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, much lesse to give them away at his pleasure; as the <hi>Pope</hi> hath done the Kingdoms of <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and others: But We acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no such power in him, nor do We believe, that any Nation is so void of sense, as to think he hath any such power, or that the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> themselves do believe it, or would affirm it, if the <hi>Pope</hi> had given asmuch from them, as he hath given to them: And if the <hi>French,</hi> and others, who acknowledge the <hi>Popes</hi> power in Ecclesiasticall matters,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154135:9"/> do esteem this Title of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ridiculous, it cannot be expected that We should account it any other; and so We leave it as not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy any further answer.</p>
            <p>And of as little weight is their other Title, as if the Subjects of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> having first made discovery of some few parts of <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> and having given names to some <hi>Islands, Rivers</hi> and <hi>Promontories,</hi> they should thereby be intituled to the sole Signiory of that <hi>New-world.</hi> But an Imaginary Title, upon such a prescription, without pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session, cannot create any reall Right: The best Title that any can have to what they possesse in those parts of <hi>America,</hi> is Plantation and Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session, where there were no Inhabitants, or where there were any, by their consent, or at least in such waste and desolate parts of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, as they are not able in any measure to plant, and possesse; (God having made the World for the use of men, and ordained them to reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the same.)</p>
            <p>Upon which grounds, as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> will have little right to what they hold, having got all which they have, contrary to the consents, and out of the bowels of the first Inhabitants, in whose blood they have founded their Empire; and not found, but made great Islands, and whole Countries void of Inhabitants, having rooted out all the Natives: So on the other side, the <hi>English</hi> will have a very clear Title to their Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, especially to divers Islands, which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have assaulted, and slain their Colonies in, which either never had any Inhabitants, or if destroyed by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> were also deserted by them, and left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peopled; so that by the Law of <hi>Nature</hi> and of <hi>Nations,</hi> they rightful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accrew to the Occupiers, and Possessors thereof, according to the known maxime, <hi>Quae nullius sunt, &amp; pro derelictis habentur, cedunt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupanti.</hi> Although if We had dispossessed the <hi>Spaniards</hi> of the Places where We planted Our <hi>Colonies,</hi> and where they had first dispossessed and rooted out the Natives; We, as avengers of those Peoples blood and wrongs, should have had a better Title to their Countries than their Oppressors, and murderers. But Our Plantations having been where neither <hi>Natives</hi> nor <hi>Spaniards</hi> had any possession, nor had left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde them any Habitations; Cattle, or other thing, which might in any sort retain or preserve their Claim or Title, Our right in those Places was the more clear, and the wrongs and injuries done unto Us by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> the more apparent; especially in such places which were sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed upon in time of open War between the two Nations (as were the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154135:10"/> Islands of <hi>Providence</hi> and <hi>Tortuga</hi>) whereunto, if the <hi>Spaniards</hi> could have pretended any precedent Dormant Title, yet, not making their Claim upon the Close of the last Peace, by the <hi>Second Article</hi> thereof, they concluded themselves, as to any such pretentions, and extinguished all future Claim and Right thereunto.</p>
            <p>We need not enlarge Our Discourse upon this subject, for there is not any understanding man who is not satisfied of the vanity of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> pretentions to the sole Soveraignty of all those parts of the World. But We have opened a little the weak and frivolous pretences, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ground all their cruell and unworthy dealings with the <hi>English</hi> in the <hi>West-Indies;</hi> enslaving, hanging, drowning, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly torturing to death, Our Countrey-men, spoiling their Ships and Goods, and destroying their Colonies in the times of greatest Peace, and that without any just cause or provocation at all, That the <hi>English</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion reflecting upon the indignity of such proceedings against their own flesh and bloud, and the Professors of the same true Christian Religion with them, might consider with themselves how the Honour of this Nation would lie rotting, aswell as their Vessels of War, if they should any longer suffer themselves to be used, or rather abused in this manner, and not onely excluded from Commerce with so great and rich a part of the World, against all right and reason; but also be accompted, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted as <hi>Rovers</hi> and <hi>Pyrates,</hi> for offering to sail, or look into those Seas, or having any intercourse (though with our own <hi>Plantations</hi> only) in those parts of the world.</p>
            <p>We say nothing of the bloudy <hi>Spanish Inquisition</hi> (a common cause of quarrell to all <hi>Protestants</hi>) nor of so many Seminaries of <hi>English Priests</hi> and <hi>Jesuits</hi> in the <hi>Spanish</hi> Dominions (a particular ground of offence and of danger to this Commonwealth) Our scope principally being, to declare the causes and grounds of Our quarrell in the <hi>West-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</hi> And We trust, by what hath been said, We have sufficiently manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted unto the Consciences of all indifferent and impartiall men; that <hi>Our Necessity, Our Honour,</hi> and <hi>Our Justice,</hi> have called us forth to the late Engagement: <hi>Our Necessity;</hi> for We must have War, where the <hi>Spaniards</hi> will not let Us have Peace: <hi>Our Honour</hi> and <hi>Our Justice,</hi> for it cannot stand with either, to sit down and suffer such vile indignities to be continually done in the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> to the People of this Nation, as before hath particularly been declared.</p>
            <p>Besides, they look but a little way, that take a measure of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:154135:10"/> interest and intentions, from the late shape and countenance that the present exigent of their affairs, have made them to put on towards Us in these parts of the World; as if their minde, or the sense of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, were altered (and not rather heightned, together with their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and jealousie upon the late Changes, and temper of this State) from what they had in the year 1588. when they designed the totall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of the <hi>English</hi> Nation; and if this point of time, which through some late accidents may possibly <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ister an occasion to lay some foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for securing Our selves (by Gods blessing) from so inveterate and irreconcileable an Enemy of our Religion and Countrey, be let passe, he may soon recover again a Power (for a minde he neither can, nor will ever want) to become as intolerable and dangerous as heretofore; and We in the meantime suffering such Barbarous usage of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen in the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> without requiring any satisfaction or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice for the same; and our whole Nation to be excluded out of so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable a part of the World, and suffering Our grand and known Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, quietly to bring home that vast treasure from the <hi>West-Indies</hi> (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving now also a Peace with the <hi>Dutch</hi>) and thereby to repair his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Breaches, and put himself into a condition again to resume that Debate which he had in the year 1588. <hi>Whether it were not better to begin with</hi> England <hi>in order to reduce the</hi> United Provinces, <hi>or to begin first with them in order to reduce</hi> England: And no doubt he will finde as many and more reasons than he did then, to begin first with <hi>England:</hi> In which attempt, if God should permit him to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Will, We might justly expect upon Us first, and after upon all <hi>Protestants</hi> wheresoever, a second part of that sad <hi>Tragedy</hi> which was lately acted upon Our Brethren in the Valleys of <hi>Piedmont.</hi> Which (if We may believe the Remonstrance of those poor <hi>Protestants</hi>) had its source and first Contrivance from the <hi>Missionary Fryars,</hi> through the influence of the <hi>Court of Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All these things considered, We hope all true hearted <hi>English</hi> men will lay by their private animosities against each other, and rather deny themselves in their particular concernments, then out of Covetousnesse of a little gain by Trade (which cannot be had but upon Dishonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and in some sort, Dishonest terms, and may be supplyed other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise) hazard the Souls (as they do of many young Merchants and Factors upon the Terms they live and trade in <hi>Spain</hi>) and sacrifice the Lives and Estates of many of their Christian Brethren in <hi>America,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Honour of this Nation: And, which is worst of all,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154135:11"/> sell away the precious opportunities which God hath put into their hands for his Glory, and the advancement of the Kingdom of Christ, which We do not doubt will in the end (all Mists being dispelled and cleered) appear to have been the principall end of the late expedition and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking against the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the <hi>West-Indies.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="order">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Friday, <hi>October</hi> 26. 1655.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by His Highness the Lord Protector, and the Council, That this Declaration be forthwith Printed and Published.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen: Scobel, Clerk of the Council.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154135:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>